Finding Aid for Martha Wright Griffiths Papers 1956-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Martha Wright Griffiths papers 1956-1976
Griffiths, Martha Wright, 1912-2003.
Detroit, Michigan, attorney, Democratic member of the U.S. House of Representatives, 1955-1974, and member of the House Ways and Means Committee. Congressional papers, arranged by term, include legislative files, bills files, topical files, schedules, sound recordings, photographs, motion pictures, and scrapbooks. The collection details relationship with colleagues and constituents and pertains to committee activities, legislation sponsored, and issues of the day. Topics of interest include civil rights, the war in Vietnam, Sleeping Bear Dunes, the humane slaughtering of animals, the economy and the fiscal policy of the federal government, women's rights, the Equal Rights Amendment, economic problems of women, and the need for national health insurance legislation.
851378 Aa 2
59 linear feet
8 oversize volumes
33 film reels
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received in several accessions between 1962 and 1975 from Martha W. Griffiths (donor 3871 ).
The collection is open for research.
The 16mm films and two-inch videotapes in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles and high resolution digital files of some titles were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
Martha W. Griffiths was born in Pierce City, Missouri in 1912. She received her A.B. from the University of Missouri in 1934 and her J.D. degree from the University of Michigan Law School in 1940. She began practicing law in 1941 but soon turned her attention to Michigan politics (where she had moved) and began seeking public office. She was a member of the Michigan State Legislature from 1948 to 1952, a judge of Detroit's Recorder's Court, 1953 to 1954, and from 1955 to 1974, a Democratic member of the U.S. House of Representatives. Following her retirement from the House, Griffiths continued in her advocacy of women's issues, particularly the Equal Rights Amendment. In 1982, she was elected to the office of Lieutenant Governor of Michigan where she served with Governor James Blanchard. She was re-elected in 1986, but was not renominated in 1990. As the Martha Griffiths papers consists solely of files created when serving within the Congress, this biographical note will emphasize Griffiths' service and contributions within that body.
Griffiths represented the people of the seventeenth congressional district of Michigan for ten terms, the 84th through the 93rd Congress. Her first assignments were on the Banking and Currency Committee and the Government Operations Committee. In 1961, she was appointed a member of the Joint Economic Committee of the House and the Senate, which was an advisory group to the Congress similar to the President's Council of Economic Advisors. Within this group, Griffiths was named chair of the Subcommittee on Fiscal Policy. In 1962, Griffiths was elected a member of the powerful Ways and Means Committee, then under the chairmanship of Wilbur Mills. The Ways and Means Committee was responsible for financial bills, including those relating to federal tax policy.
In Congress, Griffiths was an ardent Democrat and supporter of legislation aimed at improving education, health, conservation, and social security benefits. Griffiths also championed women's issues. She sought through legislation to remove inequities in the payment of social security benefits and other government programs. And from 1959 until her retirement from office, she sponsored a resolution in the House proposing an equal rights amendment to the Constitution.
The Griffiths collection consists primarily of correspondence exchanged with constituents and lobbying groups on matters of pending or proposed legislation and on topics of current interest. The collection's great value is its documentation of the workings of this one congressional office and its perspective on the issues confronting the nation in the period of 1955 to 1974. With the Democrats in control of the Congress, these years witnessed legislative efforts to use the power of the Federal Government to rectify the ills of society on matters of civil rights, assistance to the poor, health care for the aged, environmental protection, and so forth. It was also a time of strife in society resulting from the war in Vietnam, tension among the races, and the Watergate crisis. The Griffiths collection documents these issues with letters from constituents and her response to the concerns of the people.
Beyond general issues, the Griffiths papers have importance for their documentation of the specific contribution of this one woman member of Congress, who served for twenty years, and who was rewarded by her colleagues with increasingly responsible committee positions. Especially significant was her appointment to the powerful Ways and Means Committee under the chairmanship of Wilbur Mills. Griffiths' files from her work on W and Means Committee detail the major pieces of tax reform legislation of the 1960s, notably Griffiths' efforts to legislate some equity into the benefits accorded to American women.
The Martha W. Griffiths papers, with few exceptions, have been maintained in the arrangement scheme used by the Griffiths office.
Subjects:
Animal industry--Law and legislation--United States.; Busing for school integration--Michigan.; Civil rights--United States.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; Fiscal policy--United States.; Legislators--United States.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; National health insurance--Law and legislation--United States.; Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); Social security--Law and legislation--United States.; Taxation--Law and legislation--United States.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Banking and Currency.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Government Operations.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Ways and Means.; United States--Economic policy.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Public opinion--Michigan.; Women legislators--United States.; Women's rights--United States.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Griffiths, Martha W. (Martha Wright), 1912-2003.; Tufty, Esther Van Wagoner, d. 1986.; Women.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; United States. Congress. House.; Insurance, Health--United States.; Sex discrimination--Law and legislation--United States.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Death and burial.; Women's rights--United States.
Sound Recordings - Contributors
Curtis, Carl T. (Carl Thomas), 1905-2000; DuPont, Pierre Samuel, 1935-; Hayward, Charles F.; Mink, Patsy T., 1927-2002; George, Emily.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical/Background Information
  The collection begins with a small series of Biographical/Background Information that including some of the newsletters put out by Griffiths while a member of Congress.
  - Miscellaneous, including scattering of newsletters, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Congressional Papers 1955-1974
  Congressional Papers make up the great bulk of the collection. This series is divided into subseries for each two-year congressional term (84th Congress, etc.) and then subdivided into the following sub-subseries: Legislative Files, Bills Files, and Topical Files. For Griffiths' first two terms in Congress, however, because of the relative paucity of materials, these three sequences of material have been combined into one.
  The Legislative Files sub-subseries is arranged alphabetically by committee name. The most voluminous files are for those committees on which Griffiths served, especially Ways and Means. The files are further divided by topic, usually a specific piece of legislation then under discussion within that committee's responsibility. These subdivisions have not been listed within this finding aid. The files consist of correspondence between Griffiths and her constituents or other parties interested in the legislation. Some of the larger files have been sampled because of the sameness of the letters received and of Griffiths' response.
  The Bills Files sub-subseries consists of files for those pieces of legislation either introduced by Griffiths or of which she was a co-sponsor. Although there is also much constituent correspondence here, the files are more substantive than the Legislative files in that they show the development of the legislation. The files usually include a copy of the bill and related background information. The Bills file for the 92nd Congress has not been received by the library.
  The Topical Files sub-subseries is an alphabetically arranged sequence of materials relating to issues, government departments, or individuals. The sub-subseries does not pertain to specific legislation but is a more general file for constituent expressions of complaint or concern. Some of the larger files pertain to issues of race relations, busing, the war in Vietnam, the contemplated impeachment of President Nixon, women's issues, such as the Equal Rights Amendment, and Griffiths' interest in a national health insurance plan.
  - 84th Congress 1955-1956
    - Agriculture (Box 1)
    - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 1)
    - Awards (Box 1)
    - Bureau of the Census (Box 1)
    - Coast Guard (Box 1)
    - Comments-Newsletter (Box 1)
    - Comments-Radio (Box 1)
    - Comments-Television (Box 1)
    - Congressional Record (Extension of remarks) (Box 1)
    - Democratic National Committee (Box 1)
    - Democratic Party, Michigan (Box 1)
    - Education (Box 1)
    - Food and Drug Administration (Box 1)
    - Foreign Affairs
      - General (Box 1)
      - Israel (Box 1)
    - Foreign Claims Settlement Commission (Box 1)
    - General, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Highlights of 1956 (Box 1)
    - Hoover Commission (Box 1)
    - Hospitals (Hill-Burton) (Box 1)
    - Housing (Box 1)
    - Humane slaughter legislation (Box 1)
    - Labor (Box 1)
    - Libraries (Box 1)
    - Polio (Box 1)
    - Publicity (correspondence) from radio, television, press (Box 1)
    - Radio scripts, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Retarded children (Box 2)
    - Small business (Box 2)
    - Small Business Administration (Box 2)
    - Tacan (military short-range navigation system) (Box 2)
    - Taxes (Box 2)
    - Television (Box 2)
    - Trade survey (Box 2)
    - Un-American Activities Committee (Box 2)
    - United Nations (Box 2)
    - Veterans affairs (Box 2)
    - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 2)
  - 85th Congress 1957-1958
    - Congressional Record (Extension of remarks) (Box 2)
    - Highlights of 1957 (Box 2)
    - Highlights of 1958 (Box 2)
    - Humane slaughter legislation (Box 2)
    - Justice Dept (Box 2)
    - Radio scripts, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Speeches (Box 2)
    - Stevens, Christine (Box 2)
    - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 2)
  - 86th Congress 1959-1960
    - Legislative files (mainly arranged by committee)
      - Agriculture (food stamps) (Box 2)
      - Banking and Currency
        - Emergency Community Facilities Act (Box 2)
        - Housing Act of 1960 (Box 2)
        - Mortgage discounts) (Box 2)
      - Education and Labor
        - Library Service bill (Box 2)
        - Nursing (Box 2)
      - Interior and Insular Affairs (proposed Huron Mountain National Park) (Box 2)
      - Judiciary (anti-bombing legislation) (Box 2)
      - Rivers and Harbors (Trenton Channel Improvement Project) (Box 2)
      - Rules (authorizing the Banking and Currency Committee to investigate the rising cost of living) (Box 2)
    - Topical files
      - Agriculture Dept (Box 2)
      - Airlines (Box 2)
      - Civil Aeronautics Board (Box 2)
      - Colleagues (communications with) (Box 2)
      - Congratulations (1960 campaign) (Box 2)
      - Congressional Record statements (Box 3)
      - Defense contracts (Box 3)
      - Democratic Study Group (Box 3)
      - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 3)
      - Government contracts (Box 3)
      - Health, Education, and Welfare Dept (Box 3)
      - Highlights of 1959, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Highlights of 1960, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Humane slaughter legislation (Box 3)
      - Justice Dept (Box 3)
      - Legislative record, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Michigan politics (Box 3)
      - Olympics (Detroit as proposed site in 1964) (Box 3)
      - Questionnaires (Box 3)
      - Radio scripts (Box 3)
      - River Rouge Flood Project (Box 3)
      - States rights (Box 3)
      - Surplus food (Box 3)
      - Treasury Dept. (Coast Guard) (Box 3)
      - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 3)
  - 87th Congress 1961-1962
    - Legislative files (mainly arranged by committee)
      - General (Box 3)
      - Agriculture (Box 3)
      - Appropriations (Box 3)
      - Armed Services (Box 4)
      - Atomic Energy (Joint Committee) (Box 4)
      - Banking and Currency (Box 4)
      - District of Columbia (Box 4)
      - Education and Labor (Box 4)
      - Foreign Affairs (Box 4)
      - Government Operations (Box 5)
      - House (organization of) (Box 5)
      - House Administration Committee (Box 5)
      - Interior and Insular Affairs (include Sleeping Bear Dunes legislation) (Box 5)
      - Interstate and Foreign Commerce (Box 5)
      - Judiciary (Box 5)
      - Merchant Marines and Fisheries (Box 5)
      - Post Office and Civil Service (Box 6)
      - Public Works (Box 6)
      - Rules (Box 6)
      - Science and Astronautics (Box 6)
      - Un-American Activities (Box 6)
      - Veterans Affairs (Box 6)
      - Ways and Means (Box 6)
      - Ways and Means (Box 7)
      - Ways and Means (Box 8)
        (continued)
      - Ways and Means (Box 9)
      - Joint Economic Committee (Box 9)
    - Bills introduced by MWG (Box 10)
      (arranged by bill or resolution number)
    - Topical files
      - Accomplishments (Box 10)
      - Agriculture Dept., 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Central Intelligence Agency (Box 10)
      - Civil Aeronautics Board (Box 10)
      - Civil Rights (Box 10)
      - Club memberships (Box 10)
      - Colleagues (communications with), 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Commerce Dept., 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Committee on Committees (Box 11)
      - Council of Economic Advisors (Box 11)
      - Defense Dept.
        - General (Box 11)
        - Army reorganization (move of army installation out of Michigan) (Box 11)
        - Civil Defense, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Government contracts (Box 11)
        - Reserve call-up (Box 11)
      - Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee (Box 11)
      - Democratic National Committee (Box 11)
      - Detroit (Box 11)
      - District of Columbia (Box 11)
      - Executive Branch (Box 11)
      - Federal Aviation Agency (Box 11)
      - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 11)
      - Federal Communications Commission (Box 11)
      - Federal Housing Administration (Box 11)
      - Federal Trade Commission (Box 11)
      - Food and Drug Administration, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Foreign Affairs (Box 11)
      - Foreign Policy (Box 11)
      - General Services Administration (Box 11)
      - Government Contracts, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Health, Education and Welfare Dept (Box 11)
      - Highlights (Box 11)
      - House, Organization of, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Housing and Home Finance Agency (Box 11)
      - Interior Dept (Box 11)
      - Interstate Commerce Dept (Box 11)
      - Justice Dept (Box 12)
      - Labor Dept., 2 folders (Box 12)
      - National Aeronautics and Space Administration (Box 12)
      - National Guard (Box 12)
      - National Rivers and Harbors Congress (Box 12)
      - Navy Dept (Box 12)
      - Newsletters (comments about) (Box 12)
      - Peace Corps (Box 12)
      - Politics (Box 12)
      - Post Office (Box 12)
      - President's Committee on Juvenile Delinquency (Box 12)
      - Radio scripts (Box 12)
      - Resolutions, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission (Box 12)
      - Small Business Administration (Box 12)
      - State Dept., 2 folders (Box 12)
      - State (Michigan) matters (Box 12)
    - Topical Files
      - Statements (Box 12)
      - Treasury Dept (Box 12)
      - Unemployment (Box 12)
      - U. S. Tariff Commission (Box 12)
      - White House (Box 12)
  - 88th Congress 1963-1964
    - Legislative files
      (mainly arranged by committee)
      - Agriculture (Box 12)
      - Appropriations (Box 12)
      - Armed Services (Box 13)
      - Atomic Energy (Box 13)
      - Banking and Currency (Box 13)
      - District of Columbia (Box 13)
      - Education and Labor (Box 13)
      - Foreign Affairs (Box 13)
      - Government Operations (Box 13)
      - House (Organization of) (Box 13)
      - Interior and Insular Affairs (include Sleeping Bear Dunes legislation) (Box 13)
      - Interstate and Foreign Commerce (Box 14)
      - Judiciary (Box 14)
      - Merchant Marine and Fisheries (Box 14)
      - Post Office and Civil Service (Box 14)
      - Public Works (Box 14)
      - Rules (Box 14)
      - Science and Astronautics (Box 14)
      - Small Business (Box 14)
      - Veterans Affairs (Box 14)
      - Ways and Means (Box 15)
      - Ways and Means (Box 16)
      - Joint Economic Committee (Box 16)
        (include Subcommittee on Fiscal Policy, and Subcommittee on Inter-American Economic Relationships)
    - Bills introduced by MWG (Box 17)
    - Topical files
      - Agriculture Dept (Box 17)
      - Arms Control and Disarmament Agency (Box 17)
      - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 17)
      - Civil Aeronautics Board (Box 17)
      - Civil Rights (include Civil Rights Bill), 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Civil Service Commission (Box 18)
      - Coast Guard (Box 18)
      - Colleagues (communications with), 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Comments and views of MWG (Box 18)
      - Comments and views of constituents, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Commerce Dept., 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Committee on Committees (Box 18)
      - Defense Dept.
        - General (Box 18)
        - Civil Defense, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Government contracts (Box 18)
      - Democratic National Committee (Box 18)
      - Democratic Study Group (Box 18)
      - Detroit
        - General (Box 18)
        - Mayor (Box 18)
        - Special Youth Employment Project (Box 18)
      - District of Columbia (Box 18)
      - Executive Branch (Box 18)
      - Federal Aviation Agency (Box 18)
      - Federal Communications Commission (Box 18)
      - Federal Housing Administration (Box 18)
      - Federal Trade Commission (Box 18)
      - Fitzgerald, Earl (Box 18)
      - Food and Drug Administration, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Foreign Aid (Box 18)
      - Foreign Claims Settlement Commission (Box 18)
      - Foreign Policy (Box 18)
      - General Services Administration (Box 18)
      - Governor (Michigan) (Box 18)
      - Health, Education and Welfare Dept (Box 18)
      - Interior Dept (Box 18)
      - Interstate Commerce Dept (Box 18)
      - Justice Dept (Box 18)
      - Labor Dept (Box 18)
      - Legislative Branch (Box 18)
      - Local (Michigan) matters (Box 19)
      - Michigan Legislature (Box 19)
      - Michigan politics (Box 19)
      - Michigan state offices (Box 19)
      - National Aeronautics and Space Administration (Box 19)
      - National Labor Relations Board (Box 19)
      - Nuclear Test Ban Treaty (Box 19)
      - Newsletters (comments about) (Box 19)
      - Peace Corps (Box 19)
      - President's Death (Box 19)
      - Public Housing Administration (Box 19)
      - Re-apportionment (Box 19)
      - Resolutions (Box 19)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission (Box 19)
      - Small Business Administration (Box 19)
      - State Dept (Box 19)
      - Supreme Court (Box 19)
      - Treasury Dept (Box 19)
      - Unemployment (Box 19)
      - United Nations (Box 19)
      - White House (Box 19)
  - 89th Congress 1965-1966
    - Legislative files
      - Agriculture (Box 19)
      - Appropriations (Box 20)
      - Armed Services (Box 20)
      - Banking and Currency (Box 20)
      - District of Columbia (Box 20)
      - Education and Labor (Box 20)
      - Foreign Affairs (Box 20)
      - Government Operations (Box 20)
      - House Administration (Box 20)
      - Interior and Insular Affairs (include Sleeping Bear Dunes legislation) (Box 20)
      - Interstate and Foreign Commerce (Box 20)
      - Judiciary (include Civil Rights Bill) (Box 21)
      - Post Office and Civil Service (Box 21)
      - Public Works (Box 21)
      - Rules (Box 21)
      - Science and Astronautics (Box 21)
      - Un-American Activities (Box 21)
      - Veterans Affairs (Box 21)
      - Ways and Means (Box 21)
      - Ways and Means (Box 22)
      - Ways and Means (Box 23)
      - Joint Economic Committee (Box 24)
        - General (Box 24)
        - Subcommittee on Fiscal Policy (Box 24)
    - Bills introduced by MWG (Box 24)
    - Topical Files
      - Agriculture Dept (Box 24)
      - Architect of the Capitol (Box 24)
      - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 24)
      - Car Pricing (Box 24)
      - Civil Rights, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Colleagues (communications with) (Box 25)
      - Commerce Dept (Box 25)
      - Committee on Committees, 3 folders (Box 25)
      - Defense Dept. (Box 25)
      - Democratic National Committee (Box 25)
      - Democratic Study Group (Box 25)
      - Detroit (Box 25)
      - Economic questions (Box 25)
      - Executive Branch (Box 25)
      - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Box 25)
      - Federal Communications Commission (Box 25)
      - Federal Power Commission (Box 25)
      - Federal Reserve Board (Box 25)
      - Federal Trade Commission (Box 25)
      - Food and Drug Administration (Box 25)
      - Foreign Aid (Box 25)
      - Foreign Claims Settlement Commission (Box 25)
      - Foreign Policy-Vietnam, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Griffiths, Hicks (Box 25)
      - Health, Education and Welfare Dept (Box 25)
      - Housing and Home Finance Agency (Box 25)
      - Housing and Urban Development Dept (Box 25)
      - Indian Claims Commission (Box 25)
      - Inflation (Box 25)
      - Interior Dept (Box 26)
      - Justice Dept (Box 26)
      - Labor Dept
        - General (Box 26)
        - Manpower Training (Box 26)
      - Liuzzo, Viola (Box 26)
      - Michigan Legislature (Box 26)
      - Michigan Unemployment Commission (Box 26)
      - Office of Economic Opportunity (Box 26)
      - President's Poverty Program (Box 26)
      - Social Security (inequities in benefits for women), 2 folders (Box 26)
      - State Dept (Box 26)
      - Statements issued by MWG (Box 26)
      - Supreme Court (Box 26)
      - United Nations (Box 26)
      - Women (discrimination of) (Box 26)
  - 90th Congress 1967-1968
    - Legislative files
      - Agriculture (Box 26)
      - Appropriations (Box 26)
      - Armed Services (Box 26)
      - Banking and Currency (Box 26)
      - District of Columbia (Box 27)
      - Education and Labor (Box 27)
      - Foreign Affairs (Box 27)
      - Government Operations (Box 27)
      - Interior and Insular Affairs (Box 27)
      - Judiciary (Box 27)
      - Merchant Marines and Fisheries (Box 27)
      - Post Office and Civil Service (Box 27)
      - Public Works (Box 27)
      - Rules (Box 27)
      - Science and Astronautics (Box 27)
      - Small Business (Box 27)
      - Un-American Activities (Box 27)
      - Veterans Affairs (Box 28)